Finding aid to the James Parker records, 1924-2005 Archives.Parker.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
- Series I. Research, 1912-1997, n.d.; 31.0 Linear feet (72 boxes, 839 folders)
  - Subseries I.B. General, 1922-1924, 1930-1937, 1947-1997, n.d.; 2.5 Linear feet (6 boxes, 56 folders)
    - Godwin, Edward William (1 of 2)., 1976, 1986-1987, 1990-1991, 1993, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 3)
      Note: Godwin, E. W. (Edward William), 1833-1886. Contains correspondence from Andrew McIntosh Patrick (The Fine Art Society Ltd.) to William Rieder (M.M.A.), with Alice M. Kaplan (M.M.A.), from Peter Hoare (Peter Hoare Ltd.) to Catherine Hoover (M.M.A.), M.M.A. memorandum from Craig Miller to Olga Raggio, with Robert Grothier (Furniture Cave), from Irene Bird, from Annamarie Dryden (Haslam and Whiteway Ltd.), J. Stewart Johnson and Margaret B. Caldwell. Contains 6 photographs.
    - Godwin, Edward William (2 of 2)., 1967-1969, 1972-1973, 1975-1978, 1980-1981, 1983, 1992-1993, 1997 (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - Ivories (1 of 3)., n.d. (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - Ivories (2 of 3)., 1989, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 6)
      Note: Contains M.M.A. memorandum from John Buchananre. Contains 4 photographs.
    - Ivories (3 of 3)., n.d. (Box 64, Folder 7)
    - Lavallée-Poussin, Etienne de., n.d. (Box 64, Folder 8)
      Note: Lavallée-Poussin, Etienne de, ca. 1733-1793. Contains 8 photographs (37.50).
    - Marble and mosaics (1 of 6). (Box 64, Folder 9)
    - Marble and mosaics (2 of 6). (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - Marble and mosaics (3 of 6). (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Marble and mosaics (4 of 6)., 1970, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 2)
      Note: Contains correspondence with Frederick J. Cummings (Detroit Institute of Arts). Contains 1 transparency, 2 photographs.
    - Marble and mosaics (5 of 6). (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Marble and mosaics (6 of 6). (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - P.E. Guerin, Inc., 1897, 1969, 1979, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 5)
      Note: P.E. Guerin, Inc. Contains correspondence with Carola Eisenbeis, to William A. Woodcock.
    - Rambouillet, Château de. (Rambouillet, France)., n.d. (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Rococo., 1978, n.d. (Bin 65, Folder 7)
      Note: Contains 1 photograph and information on 46.46.268.
    - Roentgen (1 of 3)., 1965-1976, 1983 (Box 65, Folder 8)
      Note: Roentgen, Abraham, 1711-1793. Roentgen, David, 1743-1807. Contains articles, correspondence (translations included) and an excerpt/translation from Josef Maria Greber's manuscript of a Roentgen biography (41.82, 58.75.55, 58.75.39). Contains correspondence with Hans Huth, Maria Velte (Mittelrhein-Museum), Dietrich Fabian (International Akademie für Kulturwissenschaften).
    - Roentgen (2 of 3)., 1948 (Box 65, Folder 9)
      Note: Contains "Copy of transcript of David Roentgen documents now in the M.M.A. Library, the gift of Dr. Leopold Heinemann, 1948."
    - Roentgen (3 of 3)., n.d. (Box 65, Folder 10)
      Note: Contains copies of the photographed Roentgen Papers.
    - [Table settings]., 1981-1982 (Box 65, Folder 11)
      Note: Includes correspondences, articles, press information regarding 12/8/1981-1/29/1982 exhibition, French Menus (1757-1976) at the French Institute.
    - Thomire, Pierre-Philippe., 1990 (Box 65, Folder 12)
      Note: Thomire, Pierre-Philippe, 1751-1843. Contains correspondence from David H. Cohen (J. Paul Getty Museum Getty) and a copy of his piece, "The Business and Work of Pierre-Philippe Thomire."
    - Tufting., 1964, 1969, 1970, 1974, 1981, 1985 (Box 66, Folder 1)
      Note: Contains correspondence with John Pancoast (Portland Museum of Art).
    - Verlet, Pierre (1 of 2)., 1986, n.d. (Box 66, Folder 2)
      Note: Verlet, Pierre. Contains biographical information, obituaries, articles and correspondence with Deborah Marrow (J. Paul Getty Trust).
    - Verlet, Pierre (2 of 2)., 1956-1958, 1968, 1970, 1974-1976 (Box 66, Folder 3)
      Note: Contains Verlet's work in the form of photocopies, clippings and offprints.
    - Vitrines., 1889, 1972, 1975-1982, 1984, 1992 (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - Wildenstein., 1977-1979 (Box 66, Folder 5)
      Note: Wildenstein family. Contains clippings and advertisements concerning the canceled Sotheby Parke Bernet S.A. Monaco sale on Dec. 10-11, 1977, as well as the French furniture collection purchased by Akram Ojjeh (1978) and the resale.
  - Subseries I.C. Collections, 1912-1917, 1923-1996, n.d.; 4.0 Linear feet (6 boxes (1 oversized), 61 folders)
    This subseries includes research materials related to six collections and consists primarily of photographs, negatives and text describing objects owned, loaned, or donated by specific collectors, with the exception of the Wrightsmans, or institutions in the case of the J. Paul Getty Museum. Each of the private collectors, Georges Hoentschel, Samuel H. Kress, J. Pierpont Morgan, Lesley G. and Emma A. Sheafer, and Lilliana W. Teruzzi, enhanced ESDA’s holdings considerably. Several sections document collectors with whom Parker had no personal relationship. Other sections document collections for which Parker authored publications.
    The Hoentschel, Sheafer and Teruzzi folders contain photographic materials exclusively. Some of the photographs are of objects photographed in their original surroundings. Initially, most photographs were placed in three ring binders; many therefore have three distinct ridges or holes along the edges.
    Parker frequently kept in contact with J. Paul Getty Museum curator Gillian Wilson, and he received numerous photographs of their acquisitions. He also monitored their development in the press, and kept an extensive clippings and research file charting their progress. The material he compiled is included within this subseries under the heading, J. Paul Getty Museum.
    The Kress Hillingdon folders contain inventories, correspondence and images of Sèvres and furniture materials which previously belonged to The Lords Hillingdon that were given to ESDA by the Samuel H. Kress Foundation. The Morgan folders contain documentation related to J.P. Morgan’s loans and the exhibition of those objects in 1914.
    Arranged in alphabetical order, by corporate or collector’s last name. Photographic materials are filed as found. Dated materials within folders are arranged in ascending chronological order. Teruzzi materials are oversized.
    - Hoentschel, Georges (1 of 2)., n.d. (Box 67, Folder 1)
      Note: Contains 30 photographs.
    - Hoentschel, Georges (2 of 2)., n.d. (Box 67, Folder 2)
      Note: Contains 37 negatives.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (1 of 11)., 1972-1988, 1991, 1993-1996 (Box 67, Folder 3)
      Note: Contains correspondence with Gillian Wilson (J. Paul Getty Museum). Contains clippings.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (2 of 11)., 1989, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 4)
      Note: Contains correspondence from Brian B. Considine (J. Paul Getty Museum) to William Rieder, M.M.A. Contains 15 photographs of room views, panels, etc. in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (3 of 11)., 1974, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 5)
      Note: Contains correspondence from Theodore Dell (Frick Collection) to J. Paul Getty and with Gillian Wilson (J. Paul Getty Museum). Contains 59 photographs of andirons, clocks, marquetry floors and seat furniture in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (4 of 11)., n.d. (Box 67, Folder 6)
      Note: Contains 36 labeled photographs of silver, gilt bronze, mounted vases, and tazza in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (5 of 11)., n.d. (Box 67, Folder 7)
      Note: Contains 51 photographs of sculpture, woodcarving, wall lights, candelabra and chandeliers in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (6 of 11)., 1979, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 8)
      Note: Contains correspondence with Gillian Wilson (J. Paul Getty Museum). Contains 48 photographs of coffers, commodes and corner cupboards in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (7 of 11)., 1961, 1985, n.d. (Box 68, Folder 1)
      Note: Contains correspondence between Carl Dauterman (M.M.A.) and Benno de Terey (French " Company, Inc.), and with Gillian Wilson (J. Paul Getty Museum). Contains 38 photographs of bureaux plats and cabinets in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (8 of 11)., 1981, n.d. (Box 68, Folder 2)
      Note: Contains correspondence with Gillian Wilson (J. Paul Getty Museum). Contains 63 photographs of stands, secretaries, tables and furniture mounted with Sèvres in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (9 of 11)., n.d. (Box 68, Folder 3)
      Note: Contains 71 photographs of French porcelain in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (10 of 11)., 1979, n.d. (Box 68, Folder 4)
      Note: Contains correspondence with Gillian Wilson (J. Paul Getty Museum). Contains 80 photographs of non-French furniture, Meissen (German) porcelain, tapestries and textiles in the Getty Collection.
    - J. Paul Getty Museum (11 of 11)., n.d. (Box 68, Folder 5)
      Note: Contains 44 photographs of oriental porcelain in the Getty Collection.
    - Kress Hillingdon Collection., 1958, n.d. (Box 68, Folder 6)
      Note: Kress, Samuel H. (Samuel Henry), 1863-1955. Art Collections. Contains a list of items to be packed at the National Gallery, Washington D.C. as well as Kress Catalogue Negative Numbers. Contains correspondence to William F. Hahn, Jr. (Hahn Bros. Fireproof Warehouse, Inc.) from John Goldsmith Phillips, M.M.A.
    - Kress Hillingdon Collection., 1946-1947, n.d. (Box 68, Folder 7)
      Note: Contains photographs of Hillingdon Collection objects divided by room and exhibited by Duveen Brothers, at the American Aid to France Exhibition, December 1946- January 1947 (Gabriel, Marie Antoinette, Rose Sèvres, and Royal Blue Sèvres Rooms).
    - Kress Hillingdon Collection., n.d. (Box 69, Folder 1)
      Note: Contains annotated copy of "Descriptions of the objects from the Hillingdon Collection and of the Marie Antoinette suite of furniture. The Kress Foundation." Also includes a section entitled "Photographs of the objects from the Hillingdon Collection and of the Marie Antoinette suite of furniture. The Kress Foundation."
    - Morgan, J. Pierpont (1 of 4)., 1912, 1989, n.d. (Box 69, Folder 2)
      Note: Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913. Art collections. Contains annotated copy of "Extracts from folder in M.M.A. archives entitled: 'Morgan, J.P. 1st. loans - general list objects delivered 1912 from Princes Gate and Victoria and Albert Museum, etc. M8224'" Contains correspondence from Uta Hoffmann (Harry N. Abrams, Inc.) to Deanna Cross, M.M.A. Contains 1 photograph.See also: Series II. Galleries / f. Galleries. Morgan Wing.
    - Morgan, J. Pierpont (2 of 4)., 1914-1917, n.d. (Box 69, Folder 3)
      Note: Contains annotated copy of "Extracts from folder in M.M.A. archives entitled:'Morgan, J.P. 2nd. withdrawal and sale of Morgan loans, 1914-1917. M8226" and "Newspaper clippings about dispersal of Morgan Collection from envelope in folder entitled 'Morgan, J.P. 2nd. withdrawal and sale of Morgan loans, 1914-1917. M8226' M.M.A. archives." Contains correspondence between Morgan, his estate and Edward Robinson, M.M.A.
    - Morgan, J. Pierpont (3 of 4)., 1914, n.d. (Box 69, Folder 4)
      Note: Contains 14 photographs of gallery views of the 1914 Loan Exhibition of the J. Pierpont Morgan Collection.
    - Morgan, J. Pierpont (4 of 4)., n.d. (Box 69, Folder 5)
      Note: Contains 34 photographs of objects as well as clippings regarding their dispersal, sale and comparables.
    - Sheafer (1 of 5)., n.d. (Box 69, Folder 6)
      Note: Sheafer, Lesley and Emma. Art collections. Contains 32 photographs of objects in the Lesley and Emma Sheafer Collection.
    - Sheafer (2 of 5)., n.d. (Box 69, Folder 7)
      Note: Contains 55 photographs of objects in the Sheafer Collection.
    - Sheafer (3 of 5)., n.d. (Box 69, Folder 8)
      Note: Contains 14 photographs of the Sheafer apartment.
    - Sheafer (4 of 5)., n.d. (Box 69, Folder 9)
      Note: Contains 12 photographs of the Sheafer apartment.
    - Sheafer (5 of 5)., n.d. (Box 69, Folder 10)
      Note: Contains 40 photographs of objects in the Sheafer Collection.
    - Teruzzi., n.d. (Box 70, Folder -)
      Note: OVERSIZED MATERIALS. Teruzzi, Lilliana W., 1896-1987. Contains four 11" x 14" photographs and forty-nine 16 1/2 " x 20" photographs, of objects, gifted by Madame Lilliana W. Teruzzi (incl. 66.192.1, 66.129.3 a-f, 66.192.4a, b, 66.192.5a-c, 66.192.6a, b-.11a, b, 66.192.13a-c).
    - Untermyer. (Box 71, Folder -)
      Access note: Museum staff access only.
    - Untermyer. (Box 72, Folder -)
- Series II. Galleries, 1910-1911, 1921-1923, 1933-1939, 1984-1993, n.d.; 0.5 Linear feet (1 box, 11 folders)
  The “Galleries” series is the smallest within the James Parker Records. This can be attributed to the dispersal of the bulk of his gallery installation and related research materials into departmental files. The material that remains pertains to four particular spaces: the Annie Laurie Aitken Galleries, the Central European Galleries (including the French Medallion Gallery), the Empire Gallery and the original J. Pierpont Morgan Wing. In addition to photographic materials, folders include publicity resources, blueprints, correspondence pertaining to construction issues and object lists. Original subject headings were retained and utilized as folder titles.
  The materials were removed from their original file folders and notebook binders and filed alphabetically by gallery name and genre. All dated material within folders is arranged in ascending chronological order. Photographic materials are filed as found.
  - Annie Laurie Aitken Galleries., 1992-1993 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    Note: Contains 26 photographs.
  - Central European Galleries. Plans., n.d. (Box 73, Folder 2)
  - Central European Galleries. Photographs., 1984, 1986-1988 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    Note: Contains blueprints, correspondence and research materials.
  - Central European Galleries. Research., 1986-1987 (Box 73, Folder 4)
    Note: Contains 29 photographs, 67 negatives and 6 contact sheets.
  - Empire Gallery. Correspondence., 1984-1989 (Box 73, Folder 5)
    Note: Materials were originally in a folder labeled "Empire Gallery 32 opened 8/19/84, dismantled '93?" Contains memoranda and label copy.
  - Empire Gallery. Objects., n.d. (Box 73, Folder 6)
    Note: Contains annotated photocopies of objects.
  - Empire Gallery. Objects., n.d. (Box 73, Folder 7)
  - Empire Gallery. Plans., 1984 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    Note: Contains 3 blueprint plans.
  - Morgan Wing (1 of 3)., 1910-1911, n.d. (Box 73, Folder 9)
    Note: Contains 17 photographs.
  - Morgan Wing (2 of 3)., 1921, 1923, n.d. (Box 73, Folder 10)
    Note: Contains 22 photographs.
  - Morgan Wing (3 of 3)., 1923, 1933, 1939, n.d. (Box 73, Folder 11)
    Note: Contains 20 photographs.
- Series III. Wrightsman Collection [Museum staff access only], 1931-1936, 1948-2000, n.d.; 5.0 Linear feet (13 boxes, 156 folders)
- Series IV. Correspondence, 1954-1998, n.d.; 0.5 Linear feet (1 box, 15 folders)
  Parker corresponded with a number of individuals throughout these records, and indeed throughout his lifetime. Most of his correspondence was discarded or dispersed into active administrative and object files in ESDA. This series is what remains. As such, it is relatively small in size and scope, and is comprised of correspondence with a few individuals who Parker was acquainted with in a professional capacity. Personal matters are rarely alluded to.
  The bulk of Parker’s surviving correspondence is with Henry Sorensen, who Parker became acquainted with in the late 1950s. Throughout the decades that followed, Sorensen served as the Museum’s “European Representative of the Department of Western European Arts,” a role which Parker sought for him. Sorensen resided in Paris at the time, and was also employed in various capacities with auction houses, galleries and publishers. He occasionally wrote articles. He always availed himself to Parker, performing archival research, procuring publications and photographing locales and objects across the European continent. Parker utilized his work, and even his photography in several Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin articles, and acknowledged his contributions on occasion in print.
  The series has correspondence from Dr. Dietrich Fabian, a scholar and author who at the time of their correspondence was obtaining information regarding several of the Museum’s Roentgen pieces for his work,Kinzing und Roentgen Uhren aus Neuwied: Uhren, Uhrenmo bel, Musikinstrumente, Spielwerke: Leben und Werk der Uhrmacherfamilien Kinzing und der Kunstschreiner Abraham und David Roentgen. Some of Fabian’s responses are in German and translations are included in the folders.
  The series includes correspondence from Patrick Guy Leperlier, an employee of Christie’s in Paris with whom Parker briefly consulted regarding the provenance of several objects.
  The series also contains correspondence with Pierre Verlet, who Parker met when he served as his apprentice for six months in 1949 in the Départment des Objects d’Art at the Musée du Louvre, Paris. They kept in contact throughout the following four decades. Verlet’s responses are primarily in French. The final three letters are from Verlet’s widow. All of the files in 1968 and several in 1969 and 1971 pertain to a series of lectures concerning French decorative arts of the seventeenth and eighteenth century given by Verlet at the New York University Institute of Fine Arts (IFA) and with which Parker assisted. Parker intermittently marked this correspondence and related materials “Seminar, Verlet,” “Lectures, Verlet” or simply “Verlet, Pierre.” Material in the “Various” subseries also concerns these seminars. In addition to correspondence with IFA students, faculty members and administrators, it includes enclosed course announcements, drafts of syllabi and slide lists.
  Correspondence with F.J.B. Watson also spans four decades, and covers all manner of topics. Watson was an art historian who served as the Director of the Wallace Collection and Surveyor of the Queen’s Works of Art. In addition to his role as primary author of The Wrightsman Collection catalogues; he was also a principal advisor on matters relating to their collection. In his retirement he consulted for a number of institutions, including the J. Paul Getty Museum.
  Correspondence with Lucy Woods of the Lady Lever Art Gallery, Merseyside, England included in this series is limited to a two-year time span and constrained in subject matter to the provenance of several objects.
  This series is alphabetically arranged according to correspondent’s last name. Materials within consist primarily of original correspondence to Parker and file copies of his outgoing letters, arranged in ascending chronological order. Undated materials are filed last.
  - Fabian, Dietrich, Dr., 1980-1983, 1985-1986, 1988 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    Note: Several of Fabian's responses are in German; translations incl.
  - Leperlier, Patrick Guy., 1983 (Box 87, Folder 2)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1957, 1959-1961 (Box 87, Folder 3)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1962-1964 (Box 87, Folder 4)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1965-1967 (Box 87, Folder 5)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1968-1969 (Box 87, Folder 6)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1970-1972 (Box 87, Folder 7)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1973-1974 (Box 87, Folder 8)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1975-1977 (Box 87, Folder 9)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1978-1979 (Box 87, Folder 10)
  - Sorensen, Henry., 1980-1986, 1995-1996, 1998, n.d. (Box 87, Folder 11)
  - Various., 1968-1971, n.d. (Box 87, Folder 12)
    Note: Concerns a series of seminars at the Institute of Fine Arts (New York University) taught by Verlet and assisted by Parker.See also: Series IV. Correspondence / Verlet, Pierre (1968-1969, 1971).
  - Verlet, Pierre., 1954, 1959-1961, 1964, 1966, 1968-1971, 1973-1975, 1977, 1980, 1982-1983, 1985-1986, 1993 (Box 87, Folder 13)
  - Watson, F. J. B. (Francis John Bagott)., 1955-1971, 1981, n.d. (Box 87, Folder 14)
  - Wood, Lucy., 1983-1985 (Box 87, Folder 15)
- Series V. Biographical Materials, 1924, 1945-1954, 1962-2001, n.d.; (1 box, 3 folders)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  This series contains biographical material relating to Parker. Materials include personal papers, such as Parker’s birth certificate, military discharge forms, college transcripts, employment documents, and financial and health records. In addition there are drafts of brief biographical sketches and bibliographies and clippings in which Parker is pictured or mentioned. There are also several drafts of his retirement party speech. Most of these documents are annotated by Parker and are photocopies of original documents presumably made by Parker. Frequently interspersed are personal cards from well-wishers congratulating Parker on his various professional achievements. A posthumous folder includes obituaries, correspondence, as well as a copy of the eulogy.
  This series is arranged in ascending chronological order.
  - Biographical materials., 1924, 1945, 1948, 1950, 1954, 1962, 1968-1979 (Box 88, Folder 1)
  - Biographical materials., 1981-1983, 1986-1998, n.d. (Box 88, Folder 2)
  - Biographical materials. Posthumous., 2001 (Box 88, Folder 3)